<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>LLVM on Middle of Nowhere</title><link>//evacchi.github.io/tags/llvm/</link><description>Recent content in LLVM on Middle of Nowhere</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="//evacchi.github.io/tags/llvm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Writing Envoy WASM Filters The Hardest Way (Part 2): LLVM IR</title><link>//evacchi.github.io/posts/2022/04/28/writing-envoy-wasm-filters-the-hardest-way-part-2-llvm-ir/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>//evacchi.github.io/posts/2022/04/28/writing-envoy-wasm-filters-the-hardest-way-part-2-llvm-ir/</guid><description>Welcome to the next installment of the &amp;ldquo;Writing Envoy WASM Filters The Hardest Way&amp;rdquo; franchise. In this episode, our silly hero has decided to put together the lessons learned in the previous episodes and define an Envoy WASM filter using only LLVM IR, a magnetized needle, and a steady hand.
Now that we have figured out how to write a WASM filter from scratch, the jump to LLVM IR is far smaller.</description></item><item><title>Compiling LLVM IR into WebAssembly with WASI support</title><link>//evacchi.github.io/posts/2022/04/14/compiling-llvm-ir-into-webassembly-with-wasi-support/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>//evacchi.github.io/posts/2022/04/14/compiling-llvm-ir-into-webassembly-with-wasi-support/</guid><description>I have been experimenting a little bit with LLVM and its WASM backend. Unfortunately, although it is easy to find examples on how to compile a &amp;ldquo;hello world&amp;rdquo; using C, resources are a bit scattered when it comes to doing something a little more specific like compiling LLVM IR into WASM with WASI support.
I found Surma&amp;rsquo;s article on how to compile C into WASM from scratch to be a very valuable resource, and Frank Denis&amp;rsquo;s article on Compiling C to WebAssembly using clang/LLVM and WASI was especially useful, even though it is now a bit outdated.</description></item></channel></rss>